We all nestle under the great tree of wisdom
Dünyayı anlamaya çalışırken
Peering out to perceive the world
hepimiz ulu ağacın gölgesine sığınırız.
From the earth
Hem topraktan
And from the rain
hem yağmurdan
We perceive its wonders until we become a white bird
onun mucizelerini görürüz.
And finally snap off the most important leaf
ve sonunda en önemli yaprağı kopana kadar...
Once upon a time
Bir zamanlar
I alone dreamed in this world
bu dünyada tek başıma rüya görürdüm.
In my dreams
Rüyalarımda
Everybody would also dream after they fell asleep
herkes uykuya dalıp rüya görmeye başlardı.
Wild and wonderful thoughts would emerge from their minds
Akıllarında vahşi ve harika düşünceler canlanırdı.
Some tumbled to the ground
Kimi yuvarlanıp yere düşerdi
And others floated to the sky
kimi süzülüp göğe yükselirdi.
Connecting all things in the world
Dünyadaki her şeyi
Into one dazzling net
göz kamaştırıcı bir ağa bağladılar.
Among a plethora of worlds
Sonsuz dünyanın arasında
Were numerous smaller worlds
sayısız küçük dünya da vardı.
All of fate
Kader, tüm bu karmaşa içinde
Finding within the tapestry their brilliant glow
bir şekilde kendi parlak ışığını bulurdu.
I gradually understood
Tüm bu açıklanamayan
That these indescribable
ve sürekli değişen şeylerin
And constantly changing things
aslında dünyadaki en derin şeyler olduğunu
Are the most profound things in the world
zamanla anladım.
Only they
Yalnızca onlar
Can completely repel the madness
deliliği tamamen defedebilir.
Only dreams
Yalnızca rüyalar
Can awaken consciousness
bilinci en derin karanlıklardan
From the deepest darkness
uyandırabilir.
I'm the one who posed this question
Bu soruyu soran da
Yet also the one who sought a solution
çözüm arayan da benim.
Saving the world with the dreams of the people
Eskiden cevabım
And now
Şimdi siz de
You've also found your own answer
kendi cevabınızı buldunuz.
And I shall return all the dreams
Ve ben de tüm rüyaları
Goodbye
Hoşça kalın
People of Sumeru
Sumeru halkı.
May you be blessed tonight
Bu gece en güzel rüyalar
With the sweetest of dreams
sizinle olsun.